<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="10"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[SCIENCE






                                           TEXTBOOK         FOR    CLASS     VI









































































                                                               2021–22]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[0652 – SCIENCE
                                                                                          ISBN  81-7450-512-1
                            Textbook for Class VI


                            First Edition
                                                                                    ALL RIGHTS RESERVED
                            March 2006      Phalguna 1927
                                                                        q No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system or
                            Reprinted                                    transmitted, in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying,
                            December 2006   Pausa 1928                   recording or otherwise without the prior permission of the publisher.
                            February 2008   Magha 1929                  q This book is sold subject to the condition that it shall not, by way of trade,  be lent,
                            January 2009    Pausa 1930                    re-sold, hired out or otherwise disposed of without the publisher’s consent, in
                                                                         any form of binding or cover other than that in which it is published.
                            November 2009   Agrahayana 1931             q The correct price of this publication is the price printed on this page, Any revised
                            November 2010   Kartika 1932                 price indicated by a rubber stamp or by a sticker or by any other means is incorrect
                            January 2012    Magha 1933                   and should be unacceptable.
                            October 2013    Kartika 1935
                            December 2014   Pausa 1936
                            December 2015   Agrahayana 1937              OFFICES OF THE PUBLICATION
                                                                         DIVISION, NCERT
                            January 2017    Magha 1938
                            December 2017   Agrahayana 1939               NCERT Campus
                            December 2018   Agrahayana 1940               Sri Aurobindo Marg    Phone :  011-26562708
                                                                          New  Delhi 110 016
                            August 2019     Bhadrapada 1941
                            January 2021    Pausa 1942                    108, 100 Feet Road
                                                                          Hosdakere Halli Extension
                                                                          Banashankari III Stage
                                                                          Bengaluru 560 085     Phone : 080-26725740
                            PD 640T RSP
                                                                          Navjivan Trust Building
                                                                          P.O.Navjivan
                                                                          Ahmedabad 380 014     Phone :  079-27541446
                            © National Council of Educational
                            Research and Training, 2006                   CWC Campus
                                                                          Opp. Dhankal Bus Stop
                                                                          Panihati
                                                                          Kolkata 700 114       Phone :  033-25530454
                                                                          CWC Complex
                                                                          Maligaon
                                                                          Guwahati 781 021      Phone :  0361-2674869


                                                                        Publication Team
                                                                        Head, Publication   : Anup Kumar Rajput
                            `  65.00                                    Division
                                                                        Chief Editor        : Shveta Uppal
                                                                        Chief Production    : Arun Chitkara
                                                                        Officer
                                                                        Chief Business      : Vipin Dewan
                                                                        Manager (In charge)
                                                                        Editor              : Bijnan Sutar
                                                                        Production Assistant  : Sunil Kumar
                           Printed on 80 GSM paper with NCERT
                           watermark
                                                                                         Cover
                           Published at the Publication Division by the               Shweta Rao
                           Secretary, National Council of Educational
                           Research and Training, Sri Aurobindo Marg,            Layout and Illustrations
                           New Delhi 110 016 and printed at Bookman                  Ashwani Tyagi
                           India, C-4, DIC Campus, Industrial Estate,
                           Muzaffarnagar - 251 001 (U.P.)









                                                               2021–22]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[FOREWORD



                       The National Curriculum Framework (NCF), 2005, recommends that children’s life
                       at school must be linked to their life outside the school. This principle marks a
                       departure from the legacy of bookish learning which continues to shape our system
                       and causes a gap between the school, home and community. The syllabi and
                       textbooks developed on the basis of NCF signify an attempt to implement this basic
                       idea. They also attempt to discourage rote learning and the maintenance of sharp
                       boundaries between different subject areas. We hope these measures will take us
                       significantly further in the direction of a child-centred system of education outlined
                       in the National Policy on Education (1986).
                          The success of this effort depends on the steps that school principals and
                       teachers will take to encourage children to reflect on their own learning and to
                       pursue imaginative activities and questions. We must recognise that, given space,
                       time and freedom, children generate new knowledge by engaging with the
                       information passed on to them by adults. Treating the prescribed textbook as the
                       sole basis of examination is one of the key reasons why other resources and sites
                       of learning are ignored. Inculcating creativity and initiative is possible if we
                       perceive and treat children as participants in learning, not as receivers of a fixed
                       body of knowledge.
                          These aims imply considerable change in school routines and mode of
                       functioning. Flexibility in the daily time-table is as necessary as rigour in
                       implementing the annual calendar so that the required number of teaching days
                       are actually devoted to teaching. The methods used for teaching and evaluation
                       will also determine how effective this textbook proves for making children’s life at
                       school a happy experience, rather than a source of stress or boredom. Syllabus
                       designers have tried to address the problem of curricular burden by restructuring
                       and reorienting knowledge at different stages with greater consideration for child
                       psychology and the time available for teaching. The textbook attempts to enhance
                       this endeavour by giving higher priority and space to opportunities for
                       contemplation and wondering, discussion in small groups, and activities requiring
                       hands-on experience.
                          National Council of Educational Research and Training (NCERT) appreciates
                       the hard work done by the Textbook Development Committee responsible for this
                       book. We wish to thank the Chairperson of the advisory group in Science and
                       Mathematics, Professor J.V. Narlikar and the Chief Advisor for this book,
                       Dr. N. Rathnasree for guiding the work of this committee. Several teachers
                       contributed to the development of this textbook; we are grateful to their principals
                       for making this possible. We are indebted to the institutions and organisations
                       which have generously permitted us to draw upon their resources, material and
                       personnel. We are especially grateful to the members of the National Monitoring
                       Committee, appointed by the Department of Secondary and Higher Education,
                       Ministry of Human Resource Development under the Chairpersonship of Professor
                       Mrinal Miri and Professor G.P. Deshpande, for their valuable time and contribution.
                       As an organisation committed to systemic reform and continuous improvement in
                       the quality of its products, NCERT welcomes comments and suggestions which will
                       enable us to undertake further revision and refinement.

                                                                                               Director
                       New Delhi                                       National Council of Educational
                       December 2005                                            Research and Training







                                                               2021–22]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[2021–22]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[TEXTBOOK DEVELOPMENT COMMITTEE



                  CHAIRPERSON, ADVISORY GROUP IN SCIENCE AND MATHEMATICS
                  J.V. Narlikar, Emeritus Professor, Chairman,  Advisory Committee Inter University Centre
                  for Astronomy and Astrophysics (IUCCA), Ganeshkhind, Pune University, Pune

                  CHIEF ADVISOR
                  N. Rathnasree, Director, Nehru Planetarium, Teen Murti House, New Delhi
                  MEMBERS
                  C. V. Shimray, Lecturer, Department of Education in Science and Mathematics, NCERT,
                  Sri Aurobindo Marg, New Delhi
                  D. Lahiry, Professor (Retd.), DESM, NCERT, BL-89, Sector 2, Salt Lake, Kolkata
                  G. P. Pande, Uttarakhand Seva Nidhi, Paryavaran Shiksha Sansthan, Jakhan Devi, Almora,
                  Uttranchal
                  Harsh Kumari, Headmistress, CIE Experimental Basic School, Department of Education,
                  Delhi University, Delhi
                  J. S. Gill, Professor, Department of Education in Science and Mathematics, NCERT,
                  Sri Aurobindo Marg, New Delhi
                  Jaishree Sikka, Assistant Professor, Department of Botany, P.M.B. Gujarati Science College,
                  Indore
                  Kalyani Krishna, Reader, Department of Botany, Sri Venkateswara College, University of Delhi,
                  Dhaula Kuan, New Delhi
                  Lalita C. Kumar, Reader (Chemistry),  School of Science, Indira Gandhi National Open
                  University (IGNOU), Maidan Garhi, New Delhi
                  Neeraja Raghavan, Writer, Girl’s Education Plus, 302, East Mansion, 2 Hutchins Road,
                  Cooke Town, Bangalore
                  P.S. Yadava, Professor, Department of Life Sciences, Manipur University, Imphal
                  R. K. Parashar, Lecturer, Department of Education in Science and Mathematics, NCERT,
                  Sri Aurobindo Marg, New Delhi
                  Rachna Garg, Lecturer, Central Institute of Educational Technology, NCERT,
                  Sri Aurobindo Marg, New Delhi
                  Ranjana Agrawal, Principal Scientist and    Head, Division of Forcasting Techniques,
                  Indian Agricultural Statistics Research Institute, IARI Campus, Pusa, New Delhi
                  Sunila Masih, Teacher, Mitra GHS School, Suhagpur, P.O. Hoshangabad, Madhya Pradesh
                  Sunita Malhotra, Professor of Chemistry, School of Science, Indira Gandhi National Open
                  University (IGNOU), Maidan Garhi, New Delhi
                  V. P. Srivastava, Reader, Department of Education in Science and Mathematics, NCERT,
                  Sri Aurobindo Marg, New Delhi
                  MEMBER-COORDINATOR
                  R. Joshi, Lecturer (Selection Grade),  DESM, NCERT, New Delhi













                                                               2021–22]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS





                               The National Council of Educational Research and Training (NCERT)
                               acknowledges the valuable contribution of the individuals and organisations
                               involved in the development of Science Textbook for Class VI. The Council
                               acknowledges the valuable contribution of the following academics for reviewing
                               and refining the manuscripts of this book: Sushma Kiran Setia, Principal,
                               Sarvodaya Kanya Vidyalaya, Hari Nagar (Clock Tower), New Delhi; Mohini Bindra,
                               Principal, Ramjas School, Pusa Road, New Delhi; D. K. Bedi, Principal, Apeejay
                               Senior Secondary School, Pitampura, Road No. 42, Sainik Vihar, New Delhi;
                               Chand Vir Singh, Lecturer    (Biology), GBSS School, Rajouri Garden (Main),
                               New Delhi; Neelam Monga, TGT (Science), Kendriya Vidyalaya, Janakpuri,
                               New Delhi; Renuka Madan, TGT (Physics), Air Force Golden Jubilee Institute,
                               Subroto Park, Delhi Cantt; P.K. Bhattacharya, Professor (Retd) Consultant, DESM,
                               NCERT, New Delhi and Shukhvir Singh, Reader, DESM, NCERT, New Delhi.
                                   The Council gratefully acknowledges the valuable contribution of the following
                               academics for the editing and finalisation of this book: Vinod Raina, Member
                               National Monitoring Committee, Bharat Gyan Vigyan Samiti, Basement of YWA
                               Building, Hostel No. 2, G. Block, Saket, New Delhi; Professor Amitabha Mukherjee,
                               Director, Centre for Science Education and Communication (CSEC), 10  Cavalry
                               Lane, University of Delhi, Delhi; Savithri Singh, Principal, AND College, University
                               of Delhi, Govindpuri, New Delhi; M. M. Kapoor, Professor, CSEC, 10  Cavalry
                               Lane, University of Delhi, Delhi; R. M. Hallen, CSEC, 10 Cavalry Lane, University
                               of Delhi, Delhi; D. A. Misra, Principal (Retd), (As Nominee of CSEC) Directorate of
                               Education, B 203, Saraswati Vihar, New Delhi; Charu Varma, Lecturer,
                               (As Nominee of CSEC), DIET, FU Block, Pitampura, Delhi. The  contributions of
                               Ruchi Verma, Associate Professor, Pushplata Verma, Pramila Tanwar and Ashish
                               K. Srivastava, Assistant Professors, are acknowledged for being a part of the
                               review of this textbook.
                                   The Council gratefully acknowledges the valuable feedback and suggestions
                               received from Professor Arvind Kumar, Director, Homi Bhabha Centre for Science
                               Education (HBCSE), TIFR, V. N. Purve Marg, Mankhurd, Mumbai and the
                               academics at HBCSE and CSEC at various stages of development of the
                               manuscript of this textbook.
                                   The dynamic leadership of Professor M. Chandra, Head, DESM, for providing
                               guidance in final editing of the manuscript and extending infrastructure facilities
                               is highly acknowledged. Special thanks are due to Shveta Uppal, Chief Editor;
                               and Vandana Singh, Consultant Editor for  going through the manuscript and
                               suggesting relevant changes.
                                   The Council also acknowledges the efforts of Deepak Kapoor, Computer Station
                               Incharge,  Muhammad Aiyub Raza Misbahi, DTP Operator; Rajesh Kumar
                               ‘Manjhi’, Copy Editor; Satish Kumar Mishra and Seema Yadav, Proof Readers.
                                   The contribution of APC-office, administration of DESM, Publication
                               Department and Secretariat of NCERT is also acknowledged.




                                                               2021–22]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[A NOTE FOR STUDENTS





                       The team of Paheli and Boojho will be
                       with you as you journey through this
                       textbook. They love to ask questions.
                       All kinds of questions come to their
                       minds and they collect them in their
                       sacks. Sometimes, they may share
                       some of these questions with you, as
                       you read through the chapters.
                           Paheli and Boojho are also on the
                       lookout for answers to many
                       questions — sometimes the questions
                       seem answered after they discuss
                       them with each other, sometimes
                       through discussions with other
                       classmates, teachers or their parents.
                       Answers to some questions do not
                       seem available even after all these. They might need to experiment on their own,
                       read books in the library, send questions to scientists. Just dig and dig and dig
                       into all possibilities and see if the questions can be answered. Perhaps, they
                       would carry some of the unanswered questions in their sacks to higher classes.
                           What will really thrill them, would be your adding questions to their sacks
                       or answer to their questions. Sometimes activities are suggested in the textbook,
                       results or findings of these by different groups of students would be of interest to
                       other students and teachers. You can complete the suggested activities and send
                       your results or findings to Paheli and Boojho. Do keep in mind that activities
                       that involve using blades, scissors or fire need to be done strictly under the care
                       of your teachers. Stick to the precautions given and then enjoy doing all the
                       suggested activities. Mind, the book will not be able to help you much, if the
                       activities are not completed!
                           You can send your feedback for Paheli and Boojho at.









                                                                To
                                                                     The Head
                                                                     Department of Education in
                                                                     Science and Mathematics,
                                                                     NCERT, Sri Aurobindo Marg,
                                                                     New Delhi 110016









                                                               2021–22]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[CONSTITUTION OF INDIA
                                                        Part  IV A (Article  51 A)


                                                  Fundamental Duties



                               Fundamental Duties – It shall be the duty of every citizen of India —
                               (a) to abide by the Constitution and respect its ideals and institutions, the National
                                  Flag and the National Anthem;
                               (b) to cherish and follow the noble ideals which inspired our national struggle for
                                  freedom;
                               (c) to uphold and protect the sovereignty, unity and integrity of India;
                               (d) to defend the country and render national service when called upon to do so;
                               (e) to promote harmony and the spirit of common brotherhood amongst all the people
                                  of India transcending religious, linguistic and regional or sectional diversities; to
                                  renounce practices derogatory to the dignity of women;

                               (f) to value and preserve the rich heritage of our composite culture;
                               (g) to protect and improve the natural environment including forests, lakes, rivers,
                                  wildlife and to have compassion for living creatures;

                               (h) to develop the scientific temper, humanism and the spirit of inquiry and reform;
                               (i) to safeguard public property and to abjure violence;
                               (j) to strive towards excellence in all spheres of individual and collective activity so
                                  that the nation constantly rises to higher levels of endeavour and achievement;
                               (k) who is a parent or guardian, to provide opportunities for education to his child or,
                                  as the case may be, ward between the age of six and fourteen years.




























                                                               2021–22]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[CONTENTS




                       FOREWORD                                                                     iii
                       A NOTE FOR STUDENTS                                                          vii

                       C H A P T E R    1
                       FOOD: WHERE DOES IT COME FROM?                                                1

                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      2
                       COMPONENTS OF FOOD                                                            8

                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R     3
                       FIBRE TO FABRIC                                                             18

                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      4

                       SORTING MATERIALS INTO GROUPS                                               26
                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      5

                       SEPARATION OF SUBSTANCES                                                    35

                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      6
                       CHANGES AROUND US                                                           46

                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      7
                       GETTING TO KNOW PLANTS                                                      52

                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      8
                       BODY MOVEMENTS                                                              66

                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      9
                       THE LIVING ORGANISMS — CHARACTERISTICS AND HABITATS                         79

                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      10
                       MOTION AND MEASUREMENT OF DISTANCES                                         95

                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      11

                       LIGHT, SHADOWS AND REFLECTIONS                                             107
                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      12

                       ELECTRICITY AND CIRCUITS                                                   116
                       C  H  A  P  T  E  R      13

                       FUN WITH MAGNETS                                                           125






                                                               2021–22]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[x


                              C  H  A  P  T  E  R      14
                              WATER                                                                      136

                              C  H  A  P  T  E  R      15

                              AIR AROUND US                                                              147
                              C  H  A  P  T  E  R      16

                              GARBAGE IN, GARBAGE OUT                                                    155




































































                                                               2021–22]]></page></pages></Search>